Chapter 49. the hyena.
There are certain queer times and occasions in this strange mixed affair
we call life, when a man takes this whole universe for a vast practical
joke, though the wit thereof he but dimly discerns, and more than suspects
that the joke is at nobody's expense but his own. However, nothing dispirits and
nothing seems worthwhile disputing. He bolts down all events, all creeds and
beliefs and persuasions, all hard things visible and invisible, never mind how
knobbyby, as an ostrich of potent digestion, gobbles down bullets and gun
flints. And as for small difficulties and worryings, prospects of sudden
disaster, peril of life and limb, all these, and death itself seemed to him
only sly, good-natured hits, and jolly punches in the side bestowed by the
unseen and unaccountable old Joker. That odd sort of weward mood I am speaking of
comes over a man only in some time of extreme tribulation. It comes in the
very midst of his earnestness, so that what just before might have seemed to
him a thing most momentous now seems but a part of the general joke. There is
nothing like the perils of whailing to breed this free and easy sort of genial
desperado philosophy, and with it I now regarded this whole voyage of the
Peekquad, and the great white whale its object.
Quiquake, said I, when they had dragged me, the last man, to the deck, and I was
still shaking myself in my jacket to fling off the water. Quiquake, my fine
friend, does this sort of thing often happen? Without much emotion, though,
just like me, he gave me to understand that such things did often happen. Mr.
Stub, said I, turning to that worthy, who buttoned up in his oil jacket, was
now calmly smoking his pipe in the rain.
Mr. Stub, I think I have heard you say that of all whalemen you ever met, our
chief mate, Mr. Starbucks, is by far the most careful and prudent. I suppose
then, that going plump on a flying whale with your sail set in a foggy squall, is
the height of a whaleman's discretion.
Certain? I've lured for whales from a leaking ship in a gale off Cape Horn.
Mr. blas, said I, turning to little kingpost, who was standing close by. You
are experienced in these things, and I am not. Will you tell me whether it is
an unalterable law in this fishery, Mr.
Flask, for an oresman to break his own back, pulling himself back foremost into
death's jaws? Can't you twist that smaller, said Flask? Yes, that's the
law. I should like to see a boat's crew backing water up to a whale face foremost.
the whale would give them squint for squint. Mind that here then from three impartial
witnesses, I had a deliberate statement of the entire case. Considering
therefore that squalls and capsizings in the water and consequent bivwacks on the
deep were matters of common occurrence in this kind of life, considering that
at the superlatively critical instant of going on to the whale, I must resign my
life into the hands of him who steered the boat, oftenimes a fellow who, at
that very moment is in his impetuousness upon the point of scuttling the craft
with his own frantic stampings.
Considering that the particular disaster to our own particular boat was chiefly
to be imputed to Starbucks driving onto his whale almost in the teeth of a
squall, and considering that Starbucks, notwithstanding, was famous for his
great heedfulness in the fishery, considering that I belonged to this
uncommonly prudent Starbucks boat, and finally considering in what a devil's
chase I was implicated touching the white whale. Taking all things together,
I say, I thought I might as well go below and make a rough draft of my will.
Quiquake, said I, come along. You shall be my lawyer, executive, and legote.
It may seem strange that of all men, sailors should be tinkering at their
last wills and testaments, but there are no people in the world more fond of that
diversion. This was the fourth time in my nautical life that I had done the
same thing. After the ceremony was concluded upon the present occasion, I
felt all the easier. A stone was rolled away from my heart. Besides, all the
days I should now live would be as good as the days that Lazarus lived after his
resurrection. A supplementary clean gain of so many months or weeks, as the case
might be, I survived myself. My death and burial were locked up in my chest. I
looked round me tranquily and contentedly like a quiet ghost with a
clean conscience sitting inside the bars of a snug family vault.
Now then, thought I, unconsciously rolling up the sleeves of my frock, here
goes for a cool, collected dive at death and destruction, and the devil fetch the hindmost.